Guide to the A. R. Gurney Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
A. R. Gurney papers
1947-2016
YCAL MSS 728
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
27.96
(43 boxes)
The A. R. Gurney Papers document the life and career of American playwright and novelist A. R. Gurney and consist of correspondence, writings, printed material, and photographs.
Gurney, A. R. (Albert Ramsdell), 1930-2017
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 38 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 42 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of A. R. Gurney (Yale School of Drama 1958), 2004, 2012, 2016.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Writings, 1958-1991. II. Correspondence, 1962-1978. III. Printed Material, undated. IV. Other Material, undated. V. October 2012 Acquisition, circa 1960s-2009. VI. October 2016 Acquisition, 1947-2016.
A. R. Gurney (1930-2017)
American author Albert Ramsdell Gurney was born on November 1, 1930 in Buffalo, New York, to Albert Ramsdell and Marion Spaulding Gurney. He obtained a Bachelor of Arts from Williams College (1952) and Master of Fine Arts from the Yale School of Drama (1958). The Yale School of Drama produced Gurney's first work, a musical titled Love in Buffalo, the year he graduated.
Following graduation Gurney taught English and Latin at a day school in Belmont, Massachusetts (1959-1960) and then joined the Massachusetts Institute of Technology as a Professor of Humanities (1960-1996) and Professor of Literature (1970-1996). Gurney has written a number of plays, screenplays, and novels. Children (1974), The Dining Room (1982), and Love Letters (1988) are among his best known plays. His screenplays include The House of Mirth (1972) and Sylvia (1995). Gurney's novels are: The Gospel According to Joe (1974), Entertaining Strangers (1977), The Snow Ball (1984), and Early American (1996).
Gurney married Mary Forman Goodyear on June 8, 1957. They have four children: George, Amy, Evelyn, and Benjamin.
Gurney passed away on June 13, 2017, in New York City.
Scope and Contents
The A. R. Gurney Papers document the life and career of American playwright and novelist A. R. Gurney and consist of correspondence, writings, printed material, and photographs dating from roughly 1947 to 2016.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; American literature -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- 20th Century -- Archives; Male dramatists -- 20th Century -- Archives; Born digital; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; Gurney, A. R. (Albert Ramsdell), 1930-2017
- Writings, 1958-1991, undated; Series I; 10.42; (24 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into five subseries: Plays, Translations and Adaptations, Screenplays and Teleplays, Novels, Criticism, Essays, and Other Writings.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains playscripts, screenplays, teleplays, and novels in draft form in addition to production files and translations of Gurney's writings.
  - Plays
    - Another Aida, 3 (Box 1)
    - Another Antigone, circa 1988; 4 (Box 1)
    - Around the World in Eighty Days, circa 1962; 2 (Box 2)
    - Cat and Dog, typescript, corrected (Box 2)
    - Children, circa 1974; 4 (Box 2)
    - Children, circa 1974; 2 (Box 3)
    - Charlie Should Have Been There, typescript, corrected (Box 3)
    - The Cocktail Hour, circa 1988; 4 (Box 3)
    - The Cocktail Hour, circa 1988; 2 (Box 4)
    - The Comeback, circa 1964; 3 (Box 4)
    - The Decision Makers (Box 4)
    - David and Goliath (Box 4)
    - The David Show, circa 1966 (Box 4)
    - The Dining Room, circa 1981; 5 (Box 5)
    - Fridays, Saturdays, and Sundays (Box 5)
    - The Golden Age, circa 1980 (Box 5)
    - The Golden Age, circa 1980; 3 (Box 6)
    - The Golden Age, circa 1980; 5 (Box 7)
    - The Golden Age, circa 1980 (Box 8)
    - The Golden Fleece, typescripts, electrostatic copies, corrected, 1968 June; 4 (Box 8)
    - Hearts and Flowers (Box 8)
    - Hit List, 2 (Box 8)
    - An Internal Affair (Box 8)
    - The Love Course, circa 1969; 3 (Box 9)
    - Love in Buffalo, circa 1958; 5 (Box 9)
    - Love Letters, circa 1989; 3 (Box 9)
    - Love Letters, circa 1989; 2 (Box 10)
    - The Middle Ages, circa 1977; 4 (Box 10)
    - The Middle Ages, circa 1977; 4 (Box 11)
    - The Middle Ages, circa 1977 (Box 12)
    - Mixed Emotions (Box 12)
    - The Missing Person, 2 (Box 12)
    - The Old Boys, circa 1991; 4 (Box 12)
    - The Old Boys (Box 13)
    - The Old One-Two, circa 1971; 2 (Box 13)
    - The Old One-Two, circa 1971; 5 (Box 14)
    - The Open Meeting, circa 1965 (Box 15)
    - The Perfect Party, circa 1986; 4 (Box 15)
    - The Pig Sextet (Box 15)
      Based on the short story "The Pig Fell in the Well" by John Cheever
    - The Pig Sextet, 2 (Box 16)
    - The Pig Woman, 2 (Box 16)
    - A Progressive Lullaby, typescript, carbon (Box 17)
    - The Problem, typescript, original draft, circa 1968 (Box 17)
    - The Rape of Bunny Stuntz, typescript, carbon, corrected, circa 1964 (Box 17)
    - Saint Jane (Box 17)
    - Saturdays and Sundays (Box 17)
    - Sunday Morning (Box 17)
    - Scenes from American Life, circa 1970; 5 (Box 18)
    - Snow Ball, circa 1990; 2 (Box 18)
    - Snow Ball, circa 1990; 3 (Box 19)
    - Sweet Sue, circa 1987; 6 (Box 19)
    - Three People (Box 19)
    - The Thursday Club, typescript, corrected, with mimeograph copy (Box 19)
    - Tom Sawyer (Box 19)
    - Tonight! In Living Color!, 3 (Box 19)
    - Turn of the Century, 2 (Box 20)
    - The Visitation (Box 20)
    - The Wayside Motor Inn, circa 1977; 4 (Box 20)
    - What I Did Last Summer, circa 1983; 4 (Box 20)
    - Who Is Sally?, typescript (Box 20)
    - Who Killed Richard Cory?, 1975; 9 (Box 20)
    - Who Killed Richard Cory?, 1975 (Box 21)
    - Windwagon Smith, 2 (Box 21)
    - Unidentified manuscript (Box 21)
    - Out-takes and false starts
      - The Cocktail Hour (Box 21)
      - The Dining Room (Box 21)
      - Last Summer (Box 21)
      - Love Letters (Box 21)
      - Open Meeting and Love Course (Box 21)
      - Old Boys and Later Life (Box 21)
      - Unidentified manuscripts, 2 (Box 21)
  - Translations and Adaptations
    - Children
      - French (Box 21)
      - German (Box 21)
      - Spanish (Box 21)
    - The Cocktail Hour
      - Danish (Box 21)
      - Spanish (Box 21)
    - The Dining Room
      - Dutch (Box 21)
      - Italian (Box 21)
      - Spanish, 2 (Box 21)
    - Later Life
      - German (Box 21)
    - Love Letters
      - Chilean (Box 21)
      - Danish (Box 21)
      - French, 2 (Box 21)
      - German, 2 (Box 22)
      - Hungarian (Box 22)
      - Paraguay (Box 22)
      - Polish (Box 22)
      - Romanian (Box 22)
      - Russian (Box 22)
      - Spanish, 8 (Box 22)
      - Unidentified, 4 (Box 22)
      - Other
        - Middle Ages, Spanish translation (Box 22)
        - Sweet Sue, unidentified translation (Box 22)
        - What I Did Last Summer, unidentified translation (Box 22)
    - Screenplays and Teleplays
      - Novels
        - Entertaining Strangers [working titles: The Guest of Honor, Human Events], 1977; 9 (Box 23)
        - Entertaining Strangers, circa 1977; 9 (Box 23)
        - The Gospel According to Joseph, 1972; 4 (Box 23)
      - House of Mirth, circa 1972 (Box 22)
      - Hurdles (O Youth and Beauty), circa 1979; 2 (Box 22)
      - Personal Effects, narrative synopsis for a teleplay (Box 22)
      - The Politician (Box 22)
      - Practical Politics (Box 23)
  - Criticism, Essays, and Other Writings
    - Conversations in Learning, [working title], a prospectus, typescript, edited by Gurney (Box 23)
    - The Winter's Tale, analysis of the play, holograph and typescript (Box 23)
    - Beecher, notes (Box 23)
    - Measure for Measure (Box 23)
    - On Conversation (Box 24)
    - A Program on Reading Plays (Box 24)
    - A Program for the Close Reading of Gibson's "The Miracle Worker" (Box 24)
    - A Program for the Close Reading of Thornton Wilder's "Our Town" (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 (Box 24)
- Correspondence, 1962-1978, undated; Series II; 4
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Series II contains incoming and outgoing correspondence.
  - Typed letter to Wyman Holmes, Tufts University, 1962 (Box 24)
  - Typed letter, signed, from Wyman Holmes (Box 24)
  - Typed letter, signed, from Louise Tate, WGBH, 1962 August 22 (Box 24)
  - Typed letter to Gilbert Leibinger, regarding "The Golden Age," with notes concerning the play, 1978 July 28 (Box 24)
- Printed Material, undated; Series III; 14
  Series III contains printed material such as playbills, posters, and other printed ephemera relating to productions of Gurney's works.
  - Love Letters, playbill from Williamstown, MA (Box 24)
  - Love Letters, playbill from Japan, 2 (Box 24)
  - Love Letters, playbill from Poland (Box 24)
  - Love Letters, playbills from various performances, 2 (Box 24)
  - Playbills and promotional material from foreign adaptations of various plays, 2 (Box 24)
  - Photocopies of articles about Gurney's plays (Box 25)
  - Children, announcement of performance at the Manhattan Theatre Club (Box 25)
  - "Tumhari Amrita," poster (Box 25)
    Indian adaptation of "Love Letters"
  - "Tumhari Amrita," newspaper announcement (Box 25)
  - Articles about "Love Letters" and "Tumhari Amrita" (Box 25)
  - Aplodi (Box 25)
- Other Material, undated; Series IV; 2
  Contains photographs and a script.
  - Photographs from "Tumhari Amrita" (Box 25)
  - Binder labeled "Cheever Script (final version)" (Box 25)
- October 2012 Acquisition, circa 1960s-2009; 11.71; (13 boxes)
  - Writings, circa 1990s (Box 26)
    Includes Black Tie, Grand Manner, Early Americans, Flea, Light Lunch, Office Hours, Big Bill, O Jerusalem, Fourth Wall, and other works.
  - Writings and related correspondence, circa 1970s and 1990s (Box 27)
    Includes, Children, Golden Fleece, The Old One-Two, Scenes, and other works.
  - Writings, related correspondence and other materials, circa 1950s-2009 (Box 28)
    Includes Love Letters, The Dramatist, The House of Mirth, The Family Man, Rest and Recreation, and other works.
  - Printed materials, 1980s-2000s (Box 29)
    Includes press materials, programs, and playbills for The Perfect Party, Labor Day, Overtime, Sylvia, Cocktail Hour, and others works.
  - Press reviews, correspondence, and other papers (Box 30)
  - Writings and related materials, circa 1970s- 1990s (Box 31)
    Includes Later Life, The Snow Ball, Sweet Sue, Wayside, and other works.
  - Production related materials, 1970s-1990s (Box 32)
    Includes materials related to Strictly Academic, Buffalo Gal, Ancestral Voices, The Golden Age, and other productions.
  - Production related materials, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 33)
    Includes materials related to The Dining Room, Who Killed Richard Corey?, The Middle Ages, and others.
  - Writings, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 34)
    Includes Who Killed Richard Cory?, Saint Jane, Let's Do It!, Children, House of Mirth, and others.
  - Writings, including House of Mirth, circa 1940s-2000s (Box 35)
    Also includes Yale School of Drama notebook and other early writings.
  - Early writings and other materials relating to later achievements, circa 1950s-2000s (Box 36)
  - Newspaper clippings, sheet music and other printed materials (Box 37)
  - Computer media, circa 1990s-2000s
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - LOVE LETTERS PART 1 2-7-3, 2012-ycal-107-0001; 1 (Box 38)
    - LOVE LETTERS PART 2 2-7-3, 2012-ycal-107-0002; 1 (Box 38)
    - Michael Torke A.R.Gurney House of Mirth 19 Cues April 2, 2002 (midi realization), 2012-ycal-107-0003; 1 (Box 38)
    - House of Mirth: Opening Music Nov. 8, 2000 use track 3, 2012-ycal-107-0004; 1 (Box 38)
- October 2016 Acquisition, circa 1947-2016; 5.83; (5 boxes)
  Organized into four series: Correspondence, Personal papers, Writings, and Performance and event recordings.
  - Correspondence, circa 1947-2012
    Materials within this series maintain the original physical organization found at time of acquisition.
    Contains correspondence between A. R. Gurney and his family members, collaborators, and other acquaintances, along with photographs and ephemera sometimes included with the correspondence. The material documents personal and business relationships related to A. R. Gurney.
    - Correspondence, circa 1947-2012; 15 folders (Box 39)
    - Correspondence, circa 1947-2012; 13 folders (Box 40)
  - Personal papers, circa 1947-2016
    Materials within this series are organized chronologically.
    Contains yearbooks, event programs, certificates, and other materials related to A. R. Gurney's life and work.
    - Antony and Cleopatra souvenir program, autographed by Katharine Cornell, circa 1947 (Box 41)
    - Program for Zanuck in the Streets, 1951 (Box 41)
    - Naval Academy yearbook, 1952 (Box 41)
    - In the Wake of Drake, circa 1954 (Box 41)
    - First Stage magazine, 1965 (Box 41)
    - Souvenir program for 25th reunion of Williams College Class of 1952, 1977 (Box 41)
    - Program for St. Paul's School 50th Reunion, 1998 (Box 41)
    - Congressional honor certificate, 2013 (Box 41)
    - City of Buffalo proclamations in honor of A.R. Gurney, 2013-2016 (Box 43)
  - Writings, 1992-2015
    Materials in this series are arranged alphabetically by work title, with the exception of uncollected notes, which are located at the end of the series.
    Contains playscripts, notes, clippings, photographs, correspondence, and other ephemera related to A. R. Gurney's writings.
    - The Anti-Semite script, 2012 (Box 41)
    - Central Park West script and notes, 2007 (Box 41)
    - Family Furniture program and correspondence, 2013 (Box 41)
    - The Fourth Wall script (German translation), undated (Box 41)
    - Let's Do It script, circa 1996 (Box 41)
    - Love and Money script, 2015 (Box 41)
    - Love Letters programs and clippings, circa 1994-2005 (Box 41)
    - Love Letters programs and clipping, circa 1994-1999 (Box 41)
    - Love Letters script (Catalan translation), circa 1997 (Box 41)
    - Love Letters script (Polish translation), undated (Box 41)
    - Love Letters program from Polish production, 1996 (Box 41)
    - Photographs from performances including Love Letters, undated (Box 41)
    - The Old Boy script, 2012 (Box 41)
    - The Old Boy program, circa 1995-1996 (Box 41)
    - Older People script and notes, 2003-2012 (Box 41)
    - Posters for The Problem, undated (Box 41)
    - Casting info and program for the Signature Theater, 2014-2015 (Box 41)
    - Strawberry Fields piano and vocal score, 1999 (Box 41)
    - Sylvia script (Polish translation), undated (Box 41)
    - Sylvia script (German translation), undated (Box 41)
    - Sylvia programs and posters from international productions, circa 1996-2000 (Box 41)
    - Wayside Motor Inn notes and casting information, circa 2013 (Box 41)
    - Uncollected notes, circa 1992-1993 (Box 41)
    - Uncollected notes, 1996-2004 (Box 41)
    - Notebook, circa 2011 (Box 41)
  - Performance and event recordings, 1979-2004
    Materials in this series are arranged alphabetically by performance or event title.
    Contains video recordings of theatrical productions of works by A.R. Gurney, along with recordings of events related to Gurney's life, work, and interests.
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - My Brother's Wife, undated; 1 (Box 42)
    - Central Park (Thirteen/WNET Great Performances), 1999; 1 (Box 42)
    - The Dining Room, undated; 1 (Box 42)
    - ESPN classic, undated; 1 (Box 42)
    - Full Motion Video, undated; 1 (Box 42)
    - On Stage, 2004; 1 (Box 42)
    - Shall We Dance/The Snowball Tape, 1991; 1 (Box 42)
    - Stage on Screen: Far East, undated; 1 (Box 42)
    - A Tribute to A. R. Gurney, 2000; 1 (Box 42)
    - Trying Times: Hunger Chic; Trying Times: Hit List, undated; 1 (Box 42)
    - Youth and Beauty, 1979; 1 (Box 42)
    - Trying Times (3 shows), 1988; 1 (Box 42)